Hello!
My name is Neil
and I want to talk with you
about electoral reform in the UK.
So, what is that?
Well I will start by speaking
about the current system in the UK
which is called FPTP.
In the UK there are 659 constituencies.
Each constituency equates to
one seat each in parliament.
In every constituency each party that
is big enough
sends one candidate each to
represent that party.
The members of the constituency
vote for their favourite candidate
and the one that has the most
votes wins the seat.
That system seems very simple and suitable.
Each constituency has one representative
who in theory best represents the issues
of its members in parliament.
However it doesn't really work like that.
People don't really vote for an individual person
but for a party and even, indirectly,
for the leader of that party.
And rather than wanting that person to
represent their region
the influence in the national
decisions are more important.
In 2015 the UK had an election.
The left pie chart shows the proportion of seats
of every party in parliament.
There the blue conservatives have
a very clear victory
with more than half of the seats.
The pie chart on the right shows
the proportion of the actual votes.
That shows that the UK isn't so unilateral
as it seems according to the seats.
The conservatives have more representation
than they deserve according to the votes.
That is a result of the fact that many votes
are effectively thrown away
in the current system.
For example, imagine I lived in this region,
Haltemprice and Howden.
There, the conservatives always win
and the seat hasn't changed
since the election in 1836.
That is called a ‘safe seat’ because it never changes.
If I was a supporter of the
Labour party in that region,
it would hardly be worth voting
and in a way my vote would be thrown away.
Even more so, for example if I preferred
the Green party in that region,
maybe I would vote for the Labour party anyway,
because I know that the Green party
has no chance.
Maybe Labour would be the only ones
who could stand against the Conservatives.
That is called a tactical vote
and that happens a lot in the UK.
Instead of voting for their favourite party,
people have to vote for the one
who has a chance of winning.
In that way the small parties don't grow easily
and the politics can only change very slowly.
So that's why the Electoral Reform Society exists.
That society estimates that in fact 59% of the seats
are that kind that can't change.
They suggest another voting system called STV,
or Single Transferable Vote.
In that system,
the constituencies are made bigger
and instead of only electing
one candidate from each constituency
you elect maybe 3 or 4.
The representatives of each constituency are elected
according to some kind of system
of proportional representation.
So, we'll see how it works by an example.
Firt we'll do the election with the current system
for one constituency.
So, in the constituency
there are these three candidates:
Albus Dumbledore from the Gryffindor party
Filius Flitwick from Ravenclaw
and Lord Voldemort from Slytherine.
So, the most important issue going on
during this fictional election
is should we imprison and torture muggles,
or would it be better to make friends with them.
The Slytherine party supports torture
but the other two parties want to make friends.
So, here's the result of this ballot
according to the current system of FPTP.
Dumbledore has 50 votes,
Flitwick has 40
and Voldemort has 54.
So in this system the Slytherine party wins
because it has the most votes.
Now, from that region, in parliament,
100% of the representation
supports imprisoning muggles
even though actually 63% voted for parties
who were against that.
You could imagine that a similar thing
could happen in every other constituency.
In the end the UK could become 100% Slytherin
and we'd immediately start torturing the poor muggles,
even though according to the amount of votes
support of that would be in the minority.
Now we can imagine the results
according to the STV system.
In this system the constituencies are three times as big
and the candidates from the 2 neighbouring
constituencies join the ballot.
The ballot papers in STV are different.
In FPTP the voter just puts one cross
on the candidate that they want.
In STV you can put a number next to every candidate
to order them according to preference.
So first we'll only consider
the results for the candidates
who received a 1 next to their name,
so that is those who are the
favourite candidates.
The results are as follows.
The proportion for each party is the same.
Voldemort still has the most votes
because everyone in Slytherine was afraid to vote
for another candidate.
We have to pick three of those
candidates for this region,
but instead of picking the ones with
the most votes
we pick the ones who have at least
a certain quota of the votes.
So to decide what is the quota,
we will do the following calculation:
The number of votes divided by
the number of seats plus one.
In this case the quota is 36.
So Voldemort already has enough votes
to reach the 36 needed
and he immediately becomes the first
member of parliament.
That makes sense because he already has
more than a third of the votes.
However Voldemort only needed 36 votes
and the extra 18 were completely superfluous.
Instead of just throwing those votes away
we will give them to the second choice of the voter.
But because those votes already won a seat,
we will lower the value of the transferred vote.
We will take the second choice from all of the 54 votes
but the value will be divided by the proportion
of the superfluous votes.
In this case the superfluous votes are 18 out of 54,
and that is one third of the votes.
Nine of the people who voted for Voldemort
had Malfoy as a second choice,
and the remaining 45 had Bellatrix.
So we'll give 15 votes to Bellatrix
and three to Malfoy.
And Voldemort disappears from the list.
The points for the second seat are now like this.
Now nobody has enough votes to reach the quota.
So we'll get rid of the one who has the least
and we'll share their votes with their next choice.
In this case the lowest is Malfoy
who has three points.
The ones who voted for him preferred
Bellatrix in third place,
because obivously they want someone from Slytherine.
So she'll get his points.
And he'll disappear from the list.
The same happens for Gilderoy.
His voters preferred Flitwick in second place.
He has four points which will go to Flitwick.
And he disappears from the list.
Nobody has enough points yet
and now McGonagall is in last place.
Her voters obviously wanted someone from Gryffindor
and so prefer Dumbledore
as their next choice.
The five votes for McGonagall go to him
and she disappears from the list.
Now it's Weasley's turn.
His 15 votes go to Dumbledore
and he disappears from the list.
Finally Dumbledore has enough votes
to reach the quota.
14 of those votes were superfluous,
so we'll transfer the votes to
the next preferred candidate.
That is Flitwick, because the ones who wanted Gryffindor
would surely prefer anything
than have someone from Slyherine.
28% of his votes were superfluous,
so we'll give 28% of 50 to Flitwick.
That makes 14 votes for Flitwick.
And Dumbledore disappears from the list.
Now Flitwick reaches the quota
and becomes the third and final
member of parliament for that region.
So the three winners are:
Voldemort from Slytherine
Dumbledore from Gryffindor
and Flitwick from Ravenclaw
Now we have one candidate from each party.
That nicely reflects the fact that
almost a third of the votes
went to each of the three parties.
The system proposed by the electoral reform society
has a big advantage over a system
of pure proportional representation
and that is that you can still vote for a local candidate.
In that way you can still have someone
who you have a connection with.
It's also good for independent candidates
who are popular only in one region.
The advantages over the current system of FPTP
are that it completely gets rid of
the need to vote tactically
and you can vote for who you actually want
without risking your vote being thrown away.
It also introduces some kind of
proportional representation
without completely overthrowing the current system.
The disadvantages could be
that it's a bit more complicated to understand.
However I think that you don't
really need to understand
how the votes are counted to vote
because the only thing you need to do
is put the candidates in order of preference
and that is easy to understand.
You could argue that the current system itself
is very complicated for the voters.
Because if they want to vote well
they have to not only consider who they like most
but also who has a chance
of winning in their consistuency.
So if you like the idea,
follow the link below to the
electoral reform society.
And thanks for watching.